<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>A life less complex</title>
 <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="/"/>
 <updated>2018-11-22T10:10:54+01:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Creating a morning ☀️ ritual 🛏🚿🥣</title>
   <link href="/2018/11/05/morning-rituals.html"/>
   <updated>2018-11-05T09:26:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>/2018/11/05/morning-rituals</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Time. I want more of it. But somehow my day seems filled with things on autopilot and all  the things I want to do are all piling up - The pet projects I want to finish, the books I want to read. There are no more hours in a day left and I want to do and accomplish so much. So I spend my time paralyzed not doing anything. &lt;em&gt;Because when you don’t do anything, nothing can go wrong right?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve reached a point where I need to do something about it. I’m at an impasse if you will. So I’ve started with a challenge. Today is day one. A physical and mental challenge. For at least 30 days. My end date is wednesday the 5th of December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current &lt;strike&gt; morning ritual&lt;/strike&gt; morning chaos goes a little something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.30&lt;/strong&gt; Wake up after hitting the snooze button &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; 3 times and being very tired because I went to bed at 01.30.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hurry while I get dressed and prepare breakfast and coffee for the three of us. The coffee I usually forget to drink.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8.20&lt;/strong&gt; Leave home and bike my kid to school. Barely be on time so I don’t have time to read to him on school which all the other parents have time for. (And I hate myself for it)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m at work at &lt;strong&gt;8.40&lt;/strong&gt; which is way to early, I’m usually entering the office with the first batch of employees. Now I can relax and have a coffee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, this is far from optimal, stressful and there are lots of irritation and frustration points along the way. I &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-my-goals&quot;&gt;What are my goals?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want more time. More time for myself to learn and to develop myself. To learn new things, read more books and to finally finish that big pile of pet projects. More time to be spend with the people I love. &lt;em&gt;Actually I want to better manage myself within the time I have in a day.&lt;/em&gt; In the madness of everyday life I come home and I clean a little and start with cooking for my girlfriend and our son. One of us takes him to bed and we run through his evening ritual. After that my engergy is gone. I want to change this cycle. 
Also; I don’t want to teach my son how I currently handle time and constantly be late for appointments with myself or with others. I want to be a good example of how to manage yourself and be productive. And teach him that almost everything can be learned when you apply yourself and hold yourself to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;peer-pressure&quot;&gt;Peer pressure&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve decided to become more personal on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?l=&amp;amp;q=%23WakeUpEarlyChallenge%20OR%20%2330days%20OR%20%23wakingup%20OR%20%23productive%20from%3Asidneydekoning&amp;amp;src=typd&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and share this challenge, because having the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4746438/&quot;&gt;social pressure has possitive effects&lt;/a&gt; and might help me achive &lt;a href=&quot;http://burrsettles.com/pub/burke.ct11.pdf&quot;&gt;my goals&lt;/a&gt; [pdf]. I want to share this daily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;challenge&quot;&gt;Challenge&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before starting this challenge with myself, I’ve read up on a lot of resources to &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenhabits.net/early/&quot;&gt;better prepare myself&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve also found a &lt;a href=&quot;https://brightside.me/wonder-curiosities/why-i-started-waking-up-at-530-am-and-how-it-changed-my-life-544460/&quot;&gt;lot of tips&lt;/a&gt; on how to go about wakingup earlier. I even calculated my sleep rhythem with &lt;a href=&quot;https://sleep-calculator.com/&quot;&gt;this handy tool&lt;/a&gt; and gain a little insight into how sleep rhythems work. Another good source of information is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sleepfoundation.org/&quot;&gt;Sleep Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, they have a bunch of interresting articles about sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;schedule&quot;&gt;Schedule&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This challenge is about creating a new morning ritual. Including the  preparation the night before. And I’ve set myself some ground rules to not fail. Not really sure if this will work, but you have to start somewhere - I might change and optimize this along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-ground-rulespreparation&quot;&gt;My ground rules/preparation:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evening preparation:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Set the table and preparing my sons lunch.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fill the water cooker and fill the coffee grinder. Can’t start the day without a fresh brew 😉&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pickout clothes(both for exercise and work) for the day to come.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to bed earlier - be in before 22.00. I’ve never had any trouble falling asleep, this usually takes me about 5 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No devices(laptop/phone/tablet) in the bedroom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My ideal morning ritual looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.30&lt;/strong&gt; Wake up without hitting the snooze button.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.35&lt;/strong&gt; Get dressed for yoga&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.45&lt;/strong&gt; Practice yoga for 30 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6.15&lt;/strong&gt; Have cup of tea and a healthy breakfast&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6.30&lt;/strong&gt; Read a book, write some code or learn a new skill&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.00&lt;/strong&gt; Have an ice cold shower to get me fired up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.10&lt;/strong&gt; Normal morning ritual when my son and girlfriend wake up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll post my progress on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sidneydekoning&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; daily and with the hastags &lt;strong&gt;#WakeUpEarlyChallenge&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;#30days&lt;/strong&gt; and I’ll keep a record on this site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@elisamichelet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Elisa Michelet&quot;&gt;Photo credit: Elisa Michelet on Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>On saving 💰</title>
   <link href="/2018/05/28/saving.html"/>
   <updated>2018-05-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2018/05/28/saving</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the wisest woman in my life was my Grandmother. She always imparted wisdom on me, she knew all the Dutch sayings and expressions. She sang her wisdom to me as lullebies. In my eyes she was The Wise One.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was also a wealthy woman and knew how to handle money. She always told me &lt;em&gt;save up kiddo, you’ll have something for a rainy day.&lt;/em&gt; She just didn’t mention &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to save. But I can’t blame her, only myself, I had to ask better questions. However she has long past and asking her, well, that is out of the question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for me - I didn’t always make wise choices when it came to money. Money has always had this mystical allure to it. And I had no clue on how to handle it. Overdue bills &lt;em&gt;all the time&lt;/em&gt;. Paycheck in? Time to spend! And ofcourse there was the whole experimental drug phase. Had my own company twice. Once made the mistake of actually spending everything I made. And forgetting you have to pay taxes… The other time I just sucked &lt;em&gt;overal&lt;/em&gt; at running a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll categorise this as ‘lessons learned’ and paid for by the school of life. It was a very expensive school. €25.000  expensive. At least now I’m wiser. &lt;em&gt;A little.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m 36 now and I’ve spend the last two and a half years getting out of dept. I didn’t know it by then but along the way I’ve set the ground work for a framework for saving money. Learning &lt;em&gt;how to save&lt;/em&gt; was for me an eyeopener. What I’ve used to do is &lt;em&gt;saving what you have after spending&lt;/em&gt;. Which, turns out is all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For every paycheck that comes in I put away one tenth. If I were to make €1800 per month that would come down to €180. I put that on a savings account and don’t touch it. Not even when I have a piece of month left at the end of my paycheck. This forces me to do a couple of things. Save. Save on my spendings, because I’m missing 180 euros per month. So I need to really think on what to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;automated-saving&quot;&gt;Automated saving.&lt;/h3&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>☕️ + 🍅 + 📅 = Starting my day productive</title>
   <link href="/2018/05/07/starting-productive.html"/>
   <updated>2018-05-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2018/05/07/starting-productive</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My mom used to tell me “Empty room, empty head”. But since our house was quite the opposite I guess I took that advice with a grain of salt when I was growing up. Recently I watched a documentary about people who call themselves ‘minimalists’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/0Co1Iptd4p4?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Documentary aside. The topic of this post is starting my day productive&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Learn to focus</title>
   <link href="/2015/11/16/learn-to-focus.html"/>
   <updated>2015-11-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>/2015/11/16/learn-to-focus</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of my code mentors always put emphasis on the words “&lt;em&gt;focus on one thing&lt;/em&gt;”. These words still echo in my mind daily. Focusing on one Thing™ and doing it until it’s done makes you perform the task faster and better. Also the satisfaction you get after completing a Thing™ is much higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my day job I have to be organized. I’m a programmer I can build houses from the bottom up in my mind. With garages and a tree house next to it. But my gift of having ADD sometimes (read: a lot) prevents me finishing stuff the same day due to distractions - internet, emails, calls, messages, links to dancing cats (&lt;em&gt;“Oh it’s sooo cute - and there is another one and another and another!&lt;/em&gt;“ &amp;lt;click&amp;gt;&amp;lt;click&amp;gt;&amp;lt;click&amp;gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My ADD manifests itself everyday in misplacing bike keys and having to go through every pocket, while on my way to work walking back to my house checking to see if I closed the door because I was doing something else at the same time, overdue bills including fines because I forgot to pay them on time, going to the supermarket with a list in my head and coming back with completely different items, not knowing what item on my todo list is more important than that idea I just had and following that for a while. And I can go on for a while. The list is endless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully over the years I learned to switch rather fast between distractions to get back on track. Or rather I can identify the distraction and not get sucked into a void that can last for hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this post i’d like to share some of the techniques I use at work, on a daily basis, to get stuff done are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notifications&lt;/strong&gt;. Notifications on my phone are turned off. No vibration, no popups, no nothing. The only thing I let slip through the cracks are my girlfriends texts - since those are important. Apple put this really handy function on their devices, called ‘Do not disturb’. Both Mac and iPhones support this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Music&lt;/strong&gt;. Baroque, Classical, Electro (as monotonous as possible). These blocks out my active thoughts allowing me to focus. Lately I’ve been listening a lot on SoundCloud.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Headphones&lt;/strong&gt;, even without music. Co-workers see this and make the assumption you are listening to music.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pomodoro timer&lt;/strong&gt;. I use Tomighty. I work in chunks of 25 or 50 minutes to focus on one thing only. Want to get started with Pomodoro?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;. My sweet Notes, what would I do without you? Or where would my notes go?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wunderlist&lt;/strong&gt;. I’ve tried a lot of todo apps, but nothing seems to fit my needs. My personal winners is Wunderlist (mostly because it syncs all of my devices)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moving&lt;/strong&gt;. I tend to move a lot when programming, my head, fingers and hands when not typing. Did not figure out why exactly but it helps me process information. This moving is only while programming, with everyday stuff I don’t have this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meditation&lt;/strong&gt;. Helps me a lot. And brings back my mind when it ‘wanders’. 3 times a week about 10-30 minutes depending on how much time I’m willing to create for it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read&lt;/strong&gt;. Actually reading on how your brain works, the way how patterns are formed and mapping that on how that applies to yourself, helped me enormously. Learning to see/recognize distractions and acting on them as they happen has probably been my biggest fight, but also with the biggest reward. Actually Googling stuff that bothers you or are frustrated about, you will be surprised how many people run into the same thing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teach&lt;/strong&gt; - Explaining the thing you know to someone who doesn’t. When explaining stuff, it works better for the receiver if you tell a focused story. So you need to think about what you are saying to get the message across.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write&lt;/strong&gt; - A book, blog, stories, notes, whatever. And practice doing so. Again this helps you focus and structure your thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last two helped me enormously since they both require to get organized first, or at least organize my thoughts before I write them down of vocalize them. Or actually I should say; it forces me to stop and think about it before externalizing it. And that is, for me, a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repeat after me:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;From now on I will only focus on starting and finishing one task at a time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this list can help or inspire you to take action in your life as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What my 6 day old son taught me about doing single tasking and preparation</title>
   <link href="/2015/04/16/6-day-old-son-lessons.html"/>
   <updated>2015-04-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2015/04/16/6-day-old-son-lessons</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I became a father. A life altering experience to say the least. But yet a lot stays the same. At the time of writing my newborn is 6 days old. &lt;em&gt;At the time publishing my son is now 6 months old&lt;/em&gt;. And yet, with his inability to actually speak and only communicate with his body, he taught me a very valuable lesson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having to wake up in the middle of the night you really have to focus on everything you do and you have to do it right. It all starts with the preparation: Placing diapers, wet wipes and fresh clothes on the dresser, taking him out of bed, undress, clean, change diaper and put him in fresh clothes if they smell funny or he puked on them. Every night the same pattern again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems simple right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly believe that all human behavior can be changed with some effort or sometimes with a little more effort but that depends on the circumstances. I don’t believe in those ‘but that’s just me/how I am’ excuse. Us humans act from two intrinsic emotions. Love and fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fear helped me get over my fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So back to my son - because I’m drifting (“You’re doing it again…” my mind softly tells me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit I’m scared. Scared of dropping my son, scared of breaking him, bumping him 
against something, dropping his head causing whiplash, basically because he is so fragile. Turns out babies are very flexible. And for a reason. When looking at the nurses that took care of him the first couple of days - they know how to hold him and take care of him. Knowing this also took part of my fear away. The other part came in the form of a realization I had. A realization that made me not want to multitask anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Patterns and rules are my only freeing prison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say what? Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ritual I formed almost instantly because of this fear helps me in such a way that it makes me feel relaxed enough to not be bothered by that fear. When putting up ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alifelesscomplex.com/&quot;&gt;safety nets&lt;/a&gt;’ I release myself from these fears. This is what I mean by ‘rules are a freeing prison’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New parent realization&lt;/em&gt;: When I’m relaxed, my son is relaxed. He feels instantly when I’m is stressed. When changing him I cannot be doing something else, I have to focus only on him. And have only time for him. Focus on him. I cannot be on the phone with someone and try to change a diaper while putting lotion on his skin. Phone calls are not important, and if they are people can call back, leave a message or a text. Or not. &lt;em&gt;“Mind - here’s to you - Focus on one thing, all you other things - form a line. I’ll deal with you later”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at the past six days - the pattern I described formed so quickly in my brain mostly due to the fear I had against it. This is now fully embedded in my system for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subsequently this fear is now gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oké I lied a bit. &lt;em&gt;Almost gone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>My brain is different</title>
   <link href="/2015/04/12/my-brain-is-different.html"/>
   <updated>2015-04-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2015/04/12/my-brain-is-different</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you know what the difference is between you and me?
The left brainimage is me, the right brainimage is you. Your brains are blue and yellow, mine is red and green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this week it’s official; I have ADD. That’s ADHD without the hyperactivity. My hyperactivity is internal and not external like with ADHD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence the red color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who don’t know what ADD is. It stands for Attention Deficit Disorder. Commonly known  “easily distracted”. Something teachers would write on my rapport cards a little too often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADD is hereditary meaning both my mother and my father have it. And there is a big chance my son will have to endure it as well. Luckily for him he has a father to guide him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADD is a present wrapped as distraction. Yes. It is a present. Because of it I can make connections between unrelated things really fast, am very creative but the downside is that I’m very easily distracted. I don’t struggle with the external hyperactivity that ADHD people have. From the outside I may look calm and composed but my mind is always on. 150.000 thoughts per second. Very hard to keep track of every single one at the same time. Jumping from idea to idea. Multithreaded and in parallel. It’s like hearing music in my mind, sometimes multiple tracks at the same time, some louder, some softer. The funny thing I don’t get tired of it, for me this is the norm. I can make sense of this chaos and distinguish between it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this have to do with this blog? Here I’ll share the things I’ve learned in the past and am currently learning. Hoping others will gain from it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>