<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>A life less complex</title>
 <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="/"/>
 <updated>2018-05-07T15:46:16+02:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>☕️ + 🍅 + 📅 = Starting my day productive</title>
   <link href="/2018/05/07/starting-productive.html"/>
   <updated>2018-05-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2018/05/07/starting-productive</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My mom used to tell me “Empty room, empty head”. But since our house was quite the opposite I guess I took that advice with a grain of salt when I was growing up. Recently I watched a documentary about people who call them selfes ‘minimalists’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/0Co1Iptd4p4?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just wow.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Learn to focus</title>
   <link href="/2015/11/16/learn-to-focus.html"/>
   <updated>2015-11-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>/2015/11/16/learn-to-focus</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of my code mentors always put emphasis on the words “&lt;em&gt;focus on one thing&lt;/em&gt;”. These words still echo in my mind daily. Focusing on one Thing™ and doing it until it’s done makes you perform the task faster and better. Also the satisfaction you get after completing a Thing™ is much higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my day job I have to be organized. I’m a programmer I can build houses from the bottom up in my mind. With garages and a tree house next to it. But my gift of having ADD sometimes (read: a lot) prevents me finishing stuff the same day due to distractions - internet, emails, calls, messages, links to dancing cats (&lt;em&gt;“Oh it’s sooo cute - and there is another one and another and another!&lt;/em&gt;“ &amp;lt;click&amp;gt;&amp;lt;click&amp;gt;&amp;lt;click&amp;gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My ADD manifests itself everyday in misplacing bike keys and having to go through every pocket, while on my way to work walking back to my house checking to see if I closed the door because I was doing something else at the same time, overdue bills including fines because I forgot to pay them on time, going to the supermarket with a list in my head and coming back with completely different items, not knowing what item on my todo list is more important than that idea I just had and following that for a while. And I can go on for a while. The list is endless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully over the years I learned to switch rather fast between distractions to get back on track. Or rather I can identify the distraction and not get sucked into a void that can last for hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this post i’d like to share some of the techniques I use at work, on a daily basis, to get stuff done are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notifications&lt;/strong&gt;. Notifications on my phone are turned off. No vibration, no popups, no nothing. The only thing I let slip through the cracks are my girlfriends texts - since those are important. Apple put this really handy function on their devices, called ‘Do not disturb’. Both Mac and iPhones support this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Music&lt;/strong&gt;. Baroque, Classical, Electro (as monotonous as possible). These blocks out my active thoughts allowing me to focus. Lately I’ve been listening a lot on SoundCloud.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Headphones&lt;/strong&gt;, even without music. Co-workers see this and make the assumption you are listening to music.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pomodoro timer&lt;/strong&gt;. I use Tomighty. I work in chunks of 25 or 50 minutes to focus on one thing only. Want to get started with Pomodoro?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;. My sweet Notes, what would I do without you? Or where would my notes go?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wunderlist&lt;/strong&gt;. I’ve tried a lot of todo apps, but nothing seems to fit my needs. My personal winners is Wunderlist (mostly because it syncs all of my devices)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moving&lt;/strong&gt;. I tend to move a lot when programming, my head, fingers and hands when not typing. Did not figure out why exactly but it helps me process information. This moving is only while programming, with everyday stuff I don’t have this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meditation&lt;/strong&gt;. Helps me a lot. And brings back my mind when it ‘wanders’. 3 times a week about 10-30 minutes depending on how much time I’m willing to create for it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read&lt;/strong&gt;. Actually reading on how your brain works, the way how patterns are formed and mapping that on how that applies to yourself, helped me enormously. Learning to see/recognize distractions and acting on them as they happen has probably been my biggest fight, but also with the biggest reward. Actually Googling stuff that bothers you or are frustrated about, you will be surprised how many people run into the same thing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teach&lt;/strong&gt; - Explaining the thing you know to someone who doesn’t. When explaining stuff, it works better for the receiver if you tell a focused story. So you need to think about what you are saying to get the message across.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write&lt;/strong&gt; - A book, blog, stories, notes, whatever. And practice doing so. Again this helps you focus and structure your thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last two helped me enormously since they both require to get organized first, or at least organize my thoughts before I write them down of vocalize them. Or actually I should say; it forces me to stop and think about it before externalizing it. And that is, for me, a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repeat after me:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;From now on I will only focus on starting and finishing one task at a time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this list can help or inspire you to take action in your life as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What my 6 day old son taught me about doing single tasking and preparation</title>
   <link href="/2015/04/16/6-day-old-son-lessons.html"/>
   <updated>2015-04-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2015/04/16/6-day-old-son-lessons</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I became a father. A life altering experience to say the least. But yet a lot stays the same. At the time of writing my newborn is 6 days old. &lt;em&gt;At the time publishing my son is now 6 months old&lt;/em&gt;. And yet, with his inability to actually speak and only communicate with his body, he taught me a very valuable lesson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having to wake up in the middle of the night you really have to focus on everything you do and you have to do it right. It all starts with the preparation: Placing diapers, wet wipes and fresh clothes on the dresser, taking him out of bed, undress, clean, change diaper and put him in fresh clothes if they smell funny or he puked on them. Every night the same pattern again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems simple right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly believe that all human behavior can be changed with some effort or sometimes with a little more effort but that depends on the circumstances. I don’t believe in those ‘but that’s just me/how I am’ excuse. Us humans act from two intrinsic emotions. Love and fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fear helped me get over my fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So back to my son - because I’m drifting (“You’re doing it again…” my mind softly tells me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit I’m scared. Scared of dropping my son, scared of breaking him, bumping him 
against something, dropping his head causing whiplash, basically because he is so fragile. Turns out babies are very flexible. And for a reason. When looking at the nurses that took care of him the first couple of days - they know how to hold him and take care of him. Knowing this also took part of my fear away. The other part came in the form of a realization I had. A realization that made me not want to multitask anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Patterns and rules are my only freeing prison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say what? Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ritual I formed almost instantly because of this fear helps me in such a way that it makes me feel relaxed enough to not be bothered by that fear. When putting up ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alifelesscomplex.com/&quot;&gt;safety nets&lt;/a&gt;’ I release myself from these fears. This is what I mean by ‘rules are a freeing prison’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New parent realization&lt;/em&gt;: When I’m relaxed, my son is relaxed. He feels instantly when I’m is stressed. When changing him I cannot be doing something else, I have to focus only on him. And have only time for him. Focus on him. I cannot be on the phone with someone and try to change a diaper while putting lotion on his skin. Phone calls are not important, and if they are people can call back, leave a message or a text. Or not. &lt;em&gt;“Mind - here’s to you - Focus on one thing, all you other things - form a line. I’ll deal with you later”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at the past six days - the pattern I described formed so quickly in my brain mostly due to the fear I had against it. This is now fully embedded in my system for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subsequently this fear is now gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oké I lied a bit. &lt;em&gt;Almost gone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>My brain is different</title>
   <link href="/2015/04/12/my-brain-is-different.html"/>
   <updated>2015-04-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2015/04/12/my-brain-is-different</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you know what the difference is between you and me?
The left brainimage is me, the right brainimage is you. Your brains are blue and yellow, mine is red and green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this week it’s official; I have ADD. That’s ADHD without the hyperactivity. My hyperactivity is internal and not external like with ADHD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence the red color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who don’t know what ADD is. It stands for Attention Deficit Disorder. Commonly known  “easily distracted”. Something teachers would write on my rapport cards a little too often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADD is hereditary meaning both my mother and my father have it. And there is a big chance my son will have to endure it as well. Luckily for him he has a father to guide him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADD is a present wrapped as distraction. Yes. It is a present. Because of it I can make connections between unrelated things really fast, am very creative but the downside is that I’m very easily distracted. I don’t struggle with the external hyperactivity that ADHD people have. From the outside I may look calm and composed but my mind is always on. 150.000 thoughts per second. Very hard to keep track of every single one at the same time. Jumping from idea to idea. Multithreaded and in parallel. It’s like hearing music in my mind, sometimes multiple tracks at the same time, some louder, some softer. The funny thing I don’t get tired of it, for me this is the norm. I can make sense of this chaos and distinguish between it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this have to do with this blog? Here I’ll share the things I’ve learned in the past and am currently learning. Hoping others will gain from it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>